<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title>Words, code, skates</title>
  <link href="http://mattdenner.github.com//atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mattdenner.github.com//"/>
  <updated>2011-08-11T19:56:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://mattdenner.github.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name>Matthew Denner</name>
    
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title>36 Years Down</title>
    <link href="http://mattdenner.github.com//blog/2011/08/11/36-years-down/"/>
    <updated>2011-08-11T19:16:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mattdenner.github.com//blog/2011/08/11/36-years-down</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So yesterday was my 36th birthday. A reflection of the last year is
something I need to do, even if you don't want to read it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't celebrate my birthday because, to me, it's just another day but
recently it's been more because it reminds me of my failings.  The past
year has been even more of a reminder and it's something I want to
correct in the coming twelve months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in no particular order here's the past year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Started a job at &lt;a href=&quot;http://sanger.ac.uk/&quot;&gt;The Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute&lt;/a&gt;
as a junior developer; got promoted to senior in January; promoted to
Principle in July.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lost the most important relationship and one of my most trusted friends
because I'm not the person I should be.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally visited New York and had the best time, even though I was on
my own.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Skated, but not enough.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Made some new friends, which is unusual for me as I'm very protective
of myself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spent Christmas with the folks for the first time in years, then
promptly didn't see them for 8 months.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Made myself quite ill for a few months.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And for 2011 into 2012:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decided that Erlang and Haskell are the next programming languages for
me to learn, properly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'm going to make the team at the WTSI the best team at the WTSI.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speaking and reading Mandarin, at least to a level where I feel I
could get by.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go back to New York, because it was one of the best breaks I've had
and I want to do more there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Present at a conference, preferably outside of the UK.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Skate more, and maybe abroad more often.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
