<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Software engineering | Words, code, skates]]></title>
  <link href="http://mattdenner.github.com//blog/categories/software-engineering/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mattdenner.github.com//"/>
  <updated>2011-11-22T19:15:04+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://mattdenner.github.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Matthew Denner]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Disagreement #1]]></title>
    <link href="http://mattdenner.github.com//blog/2011/11/22/disagreement--1/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-22T18:19:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mattdenner.github.com//blog/2011/11/22/disagreement--1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Work has been a little stressful over the last few months, which is a
whole other blog post at some point, but during the course of this I've
had several disagreements with people that I've not been able to argue a
reason why either option is better.  I've had gut feelings but, without
being able to rely on the trusted "gut", it's hard to convince people
that your opinion is in any way as valid as theirs.</p>

<p>I think the ability to see others view points is something important,
especially in an environment such as software development, but when
those individuals have strong views, or a stubborn attachment to them,
then you appear weak them.  I personally don't think of myself as weak,
in that respect, but it bothers me that I can't convince people to even
consider my opinion in some cases, and that worries me that we, as a
team, will over look something.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Here's a case in point:</p>

<p>There are, to me, two camps of people in the object oriented world:
those that believe in a large forest of small trees, and those that want
one big tree.</p>

<p>In Ruby code, these two views look like this, in the typical scenario of
describing vehicles:</p>

<p><code>ruby
class Vehicle ; end
class Car &lt; Vehicle ; end
class Bus &lt; Vehicle ; end
class Lorry &lt; Vehicle ; end
class Ferrari &lt; Car ; end
class Delorian &lt; Car ; end
class Scania &lt; Lorry ; end
</code></p>

<p>And so on (please don't point out that the names I've used are really
instances of a Manufacturer class, that's not what I'm trying to show
here).  This is a big tree: everything is in one long hierarchy of
classes because, on some level, they all fit into that tree.</p>

<p>The other alternative is the large forest:</p>

<p>``` ruby
module Car ; end
module Bus ; end
module Lorry ; end</p>

<p>class Ferrari ; include Car ; end
class Delorian ; include Car ; end
class Scania ; include Lorry ; end
```</p>

<p>The idea being that anything that includes Car shares that common car
behaviour (maybe the number of wheels are 4, maybe the license you need
to drive it is non-specific); as do those including Lorry.</p>

<p>What the latter say is that you cannot substitute an instance of Scania
for an instance of Ferrari: who would want to race a Scania lorry in an
F1 competition?  Yes, I know, in Ruby you can because you just require
the object to respond to certain methods, but that's another argument I
have with people about using the language, not imposing some static type
view point on a dynamic language.</p>

<p>The problem is that, when I argue the case for a large forest those
people who believe in big trees put up a stronger, or more aggressive,
viewpoint.  In my experience, having worked with some extremely good
software engineers in varying languages, the better developers lean
towards the large forest because they see hierarchies as somewhat
brittle: the classic of adding Aeroplane to these two situations is
easier in the latter but people still try to push and shove it into
their single hierarchy, after all, a Vehicle has an engine, so does an
Aeroplane.</p>

<p>I've rarely come across good software engineers who blankly refuse to
even consider one view when they have the opposite, and it angers me
because I see both, I just prefer the latter in my gut.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
